sit in workshop two which is probably
stupid but then I don't lose my voice by
the end of the residency well yeah it
was that was one of the weird things
that really changed for me when I quit
teaching full-time was my vocal cords do
not get the kind of workout they used to
does that yes I kept thinking why am I
losing my voice and I got the only thing
I can figure out us is recording yes ooh
me me yeah I'm just going to go and then
the reason I kind of added that was this
is for DSLR apparently will go for like
twenty four minutes but then it fills up
for gigs I'm going to have to get like
at the restart efficiency so if I forget
to do that yeah the other one will be
justice for food
and so you know I kind of think that the
interview will be I mean I've really
pretty familiar right now with your work
but it's going to focus more on the
practice so it's not so much like I'm
not going to prompt you by book cause I
like kind of imagery or something that
you were doing certain parts of your
career but I just want you to kind of go
and forget whatever we can from that and
and think about practice and how it's
changed and all that sort of thing is
kind of mean that's a real focus but
anything you think of the time and if
you repeat yourself the time okay and if
I'm annoying or if you're definitely
like down with the questions like okay
let's go okay I mean you know I'm just
trying to throw everything out okay
first time and we'll see what see how it
goes okay okay yeah okay
all right so just forgive you call me a
call when you're done yeah so I'm just
gonna go into town and have some coffee
or so I'm going okay work alrighty so oh
all right did you call me don't you need
me to come back okay ah I can fix it
okay so we'll get started so I have sort
of like a couple different sections of
interview questions that I'm going to
ask the first are based on a survey that
I did of other kind of more emerging
writers about their kind of digital
practices generally and so that's more
of kind of little be kind of we'll go
through it somewhat quickly and then
I'll ask you about your sort of practice
generally and how that's changed and
then I'll ask you a little bit about
your computer more about your computer
use and then about teaching
correspondence and in the photos I've
seen is that how you pronounce them yeah
that's good
um so so yeah is that something would
you give it so if you would please state
for the camera your name your date of
birth and where we are okay I'm now Van
Winkle and I'm born October 24 1951 and
we're in Liberty Lake Washington and
you've been living here for I've been in
the Spokane area since 1990
okay but my husband I just moved out
here this little condo in O seven the
other ways it's beautiful you'd like
okay so here you're sort of a sort of
digital in and physical sort of quick
questions but so what genre is do you
work in the writer poetry primarily but
also I write your stories what kinds of
devices do you own or have access to for
writing um well for writing electronic
devices yeah yeah that's okay yeah I I
work on three different computers this
big iMac here that I use and then I have
a laptop map Mac and then I also have an
iPad okay are you right on the other I
have a keyboard oh extension for it and
what uh what what like program you used
to write in fact I use pages on that be
okay and then I move it when i IE mail
it to myself and then I move it into
word okay now use that when I'm on the
road when you're on the road iPad and
yeah and you're on the road quite a bit
when I go to Vermont
oh hold on you go to Vermont when I'm
doing any kind of traveling you don't
travel with the laptop discovery right
yeah I don't really take the laptop with
me I have an older laptop and it's those
pretty heavy yes they are
okay so you haven't two three devices
and you use your Mac user program yeah I
have I'm clueless with the PC Louis okay
and your primary so what would you call
one of these devices your primary device
this one
got it mm-hm and then so how do you any
sort of set this but how do you manage
your files between the devices you email
them to yourself you know put the iPad I
email files to myself do I do it any
other way
with the laptop I have put things on a
memory stick and move things back and
forth that way when I have to give a
presentation in Vermont and I have been
doing a lot of PowerPoint things lately
with art text and art yeah I I'll bring
up and then we stick and use the set up
if they have it to college there and all
good snacks and a good tech person who
photos have to get it set up yeah
so you so for your work to you right now
are you working exclusively on computers
or do you kind of go between the
physical and digital environments at all
highs work in longhand okay on yellow
legal tablets or just whatever I have
different notebooks that I have that's
what all these no people are here are my
various writing projects in process they
each get their own little notebook and I
work longhand for gosh I don't know at
least three or four more drafts okay at
least sometimes more like 10 or 12 it
just depends some things give me more
than others before I will type something
all right and I we're going to come back
to that okay how do you what's the
transition from notebook into digital
what else you type it out yourself yeah
yeah and is that is that a moment of
revision for you usually yeah okay yeah
okay and and then I'll probably revise
then once I get it into a document and
I'll probably revise it yeah
again a number
time okay and I you know I'm doing
different no revision operations me
we're going to go we're definitely going
to talk about occasion warned outside I
just yeah this is the sort of life
lol thing with over hell yeah Seward's
okay and then so these are the questions
of professionally I'm interested in so
how do you then save these notebooks and
your prewriting and all that I mean is
there a you just keep them in a box
somewhere or this is they this is this
like your older one yeah I have
described they're all down there on a
shelf all down there on the show yeah
okay okay and then in your your actual
digital files how do you save those you
save them just as Word docs um yeah I
save miss Word docs and then when I'm
done with them you know when the books
are published then I I just put them on
our backup disk and take them off my
book with my hard drive here do you
print out your writing to provide you
often when it gets to the computer stage
yeah not so much
okay I'm just looking on the screen and
for quite a while so then and in this
sort of last section of this is how do
you back up your work and you say like
when you're finished with something you
put it on a external hard drive yes is
that your time digital archival backups
right okay and you don't use any
cloud-based systems like a Dropbox or I
arrived yeah I do use Dropbox uh-huh but
not really so much for backup but to
send things to people to send days and
sheraton yeah
our files saved in more than one
location then um well I have I do have a
backup Drive and okay so on the hard
drive hi pewter yeah I had in the back
okay yeah well you keep print copies of
your final dress or oh yeah okay so that
you have like a paper archive as well
yes okay
how do you keep what do you do how do
you keep that just in boxes like the
notebooks kind over yeah they're usually
with the notebooks are yeah I just once
I'd print them out I do some final kind
of tinkering usually like the galleys
and everything and I'll keep a copy of
the galleys when the book is actually
coming out and that gets filed with the
notebooks then when I'm done with it and
then the sort of over business and the
question for me personally am the
librarian said have you ever received or
sought out information about methods for
digital archiving activity for like best
practices no okay
and when you'd be interested in
information about that or you know maybe
I was thinking about that the other day
a couple of I was thinking about making
of a book of selected stories from my
for books Astoria and realizing that my
first two books of stories I don't know
if I can access the computer files of
them anymore they're they're like on Oh
floppy disk or zip discorso changes and
I just I don't know if I could yeah you
know does that mean I'm going to have to
retype those suckers or are you usually
like yeah if I could even find them yeah
yes yeah there's that because you know
when we moved out here yeah so that
would be a major task to locate and
write so I could probably use some help
with that okay yeah I know that's and
that's definitely something that you
know that that kind of period especially
the 90s if it's all the different we're
probably a player and then all the
different ways of saving them right put
people in yeah when you do okay so that
was sort of the quick okay quick
beginning I'm just going to check this
is make sure
okay um that's working so we'll do a set
so this is going to be more about the
kind of overview of your writing
practices and generally and so the sort
of first couple questions are just sort
of broad and anything elaborate as much
there were as little as you'd like but
so how long have you been writing in a
more professional capacity and like in a
way that would sort of I don't know
feeding you or giving you some sort of I
mean even even if I can MFA might be a
kind of professional sort of like when
you think you started writing kind of
distant as years as your vocation
whereas something that led to something
that would be your vocation describe
teaching yeah no I I guess since
graduate school I went to graduate
school and I thought I would just do
that for a year that was my plan I would
go to graduate school and creative
writing for a year and then I would go
to medical school I had been a pre-med
major after college but when I got to
grad school I was just probably happy
doing my writing thing and I just I
never looked back so I just I worked I
started my so-called practice there
where I worked every day on my writing
and roof that was 1975 where was it I
went to the University Denver University
Denver I mean was that it one year
program yeah no I actually stayed the
regular two years stay - yeah and got
your anything and then so my uh my next
question is sort of like I'm interested
in kind of like how you would describe
the arc of your career like where you
went from there and just kind of a
general okay elaborate or as elaborate
as you want to be sort of background
there yeah and from there I taught for I
got my first teaching job at Marymount
College of Kansas now defunct okay
so I taught there for three years and
then I got a job at Lake Forest College
just north of Chicago and I cut there
for eleven years
and then I came out here in 1990 oh and
I've been here ever since and you can
you retired yeah I retired from Eastern
and oh seven okay but you're continuing
to teach and at Fermont College so so
now we're going to get kind of we've
always been nervous get to the kind of
specific writing practices sort of
generally and I have it kind of
delineated into kind of three stages a
sort of drafting prewriting notebook
stage and then a revision stage and then
a kind of organizational archival stages
and what I'd like to do is sort of go
stage by stage and ask you about kind of
your practices in the beginning and how
those have changed for each stage but if
that doesn't make sense to you we can do
it a different no I said that makes it
okay so uh I guess I'm I would like to
first start talking about sort of ways
you you draft and create your work
initially so what is your sort of
typical compositional practice
especially when you and I'm interested
right now and kind of like when you
first started writing how are you
generating and composing your writing at
that point so yeah early on I one of the
things that's different now it has been
for a long time early on I was probably
just work on a poem so I would you know
right I would have a page in my notebook
or whatever what's the blinds and move
things around on the page and then I
would have a another page in the book
with a different poem but over the years
I started working on maybe two or three
palms almost kind of simultaneously on
the same page which feels kind of nutty
but I was what I was experiencing that
kind of led me this way was that a lot
of times things would be coming to me
images lines that didn't seem to belong
to the poem I thought I was working on
and so I realized that it might be
helpful to us to not confine myself so
that's why that was one of the sort of
main transitions that I've noticed in my
I think that happened maybe you know
sort of halfway along okay maybe late
eighties or so I started experimenting
with that and I liked it yeah I liked
having just a page there'd be a poem
going down one margin and then maybe
done another margins and across the
bottom something like that on Island Oh
on it on one page and then a lot of
times what would happen is I did I
didn't like one or two or all three of
them and eventually maybe just one of
those poems would kind of gel and then
get it's all fake okay well I found out
in the notebook yeah okay and and that
and then so is that could you put that
in a certainty book or was that just
sort of gradual yeah I think I I really
started experimenting with that was a
book called beside ourselves just maybe
kind of in the middle somewhere there
yeah yeah that was really awesome maybe
the first book that was more kind of
deliberate series but yeah like I think
I can kinda she's letting I can kind of
figure out where that happened oh yeah
kind of like yeah and then I liked I
liked that I liked looking in series so
much when I was writing that book that I
also just decided that I wanted to keep
moving in that direction
I liked the series pause okay doing
those yeah yeah and they maybe learn
some self more to that kind of practice
with several palms kind of happening at
the same time in the early draft stages
yeah and then how is that different tuna
from your fiction right uh-huh yeah
I don't really see a lot of similarities
between writing stories and writing
poems in terms of the drafting process
well in terms of space okay
stories are really different and one of
the first things they learn about
writing stories in the drafting process
was oh it kind of helps to know a few
things about what's going to happen in
this story through not unlike a poem
where you're kind of launching into the
unknown
it seems helpful to have like a few
scenes in mind you know what some of the
lines of tension
storylines kind of have a few things
yeah almost not an outline but I often
had would writes down four or five kind
of sentences that would later become
scenes and that would be like on one
page of the notebook notebook or you
know just to scrap a paper in the car on
driving okay and yeah then you grab
those cotton paper and put them in the
notebook cause it become like does it
accumulate all your sort all that sort
of detritus of composition now once I
write the scene I throw the piece of
paper right yeah all right but the but
then I my process in making the stories
would be I write like I try to write a
scene a day or so in the initial
drafting phase and I just try to stay
with that scene and you know blow out
the edges often it's like three times as
long as what's going to actually be in
the final story okay usually I'm
compressing compressing compressing but
initially I just trying to look around
and see what's happening in the
periphery and just sort of stain once
one scene at a time and I don't worry
about the order I'm not writing the
first scene first I often write start
with the middle scene in fact I kind
know I'm writing the middle scene and
then I just I move
in the chronology of the story I because
I you know I have my little list and
often when I'm working on one scene I'll
think of another sin and I just write it
on another piece of paper like just
again a sentence settles kind of comment
yeah so I don't forget Oh what's up see
on this but so it's they're very the
process is really different it takes me
I like when a story is happening when
I'm getting that early draft comes
really fast I hate it I hate it I hate
it because it takes all my time I have
been known to cancel classes I'm sick
today sorry I can't come in today
[Laughter]
because I feel like I'm going to lose it
okay so I when you said it it's
happening it feels like like it's come
to you it's like I mean it's not like an
inspiration but it's just like
accumulation or so much is going on you
know I go out and I take a walk every
afternoon this apartment we actually
part my writing process to take a walk
in the afternoon and shut up I'm just
trying to walk the people are talking in
my head and so it's just it feels like
it's just kind of sits over powering
saying when I'm working on a story it
just comes over me and it wakes me up in
the morning people wake me up in the
morning they are chattering away is it
it's very unnerving
and I often push back at a story until I
am really sure that I have you know
quite a few of the building blocks in
place because otherwise it it just seems
like a struggle in a fight and it's
going to occupy it takes it takes me
about ten days of like ten hour days in
a row ten ten-hour day well it's for one
story for a story and this is all
hundred into yeah okay and it's just
incredible no I mean I'm I guess you're
saving a minute yeah I'm down
yeah but not with the hands with the
brains and then you know it's so much
because I don't I don't know how other
writers do this because I'm not writing
the scenes in order I'm kind of
deliberately writing them out of order
just I write the scene I see most
clearly in my mind first and not worry
about where it's going to go then then I
just put the whole thing away for a long
time that initial mess of a draft and
then worry later about kind of arranging
the scenes I'm often moving things
around not based on when they happened
but what's more interesting to come next
okay
and so when were you studying fiction as
well as poetry in your graduate school
or did when did you start to write these
stories well I was um I did take a
fiction writing class in grad school I
was in I was in the poetry group but we
had to take a fiction class and I was
terrible I was terrible at it because I
didn't have any sense of what made a
story yeah but when I started teaching
it's especially when I moved to Lake
Forest College I they thought well any
poet can teach fiction writing you know
it's debatable if we can get a fiction
writer who can teach poetry so they
hired thinking you know that I could
figure it out so I think I just
accidentally taught myself to write
fiction by trying to help my students
make their stories better and trying to
diagnose and what does this story need I
remember so many days walking to my
fiction writing class and trying to
think about what I was going to say to
this writer about her story you know how
to how to address its trouble
and I realized that I was internalizing
all of all this and then the first
time I got a sabbatical on I remember I
was driving into Chicago on a little for
a little adventure for the day and I'm
so happy I had the sabbatical I was
going to work on poems of course and I
got this idea for a story and I wrote I
remember I was just writing on my car
see fine
driving this this little note to myself
about what the story kind of just a
synopsis like one sentence of what it
would be by the time I got into Chicago
I had five story synopses written on
this piece of paper well and then I just
came home and that's when I did from my
own radical I will I will a bunch of
stories analysis first book of stories
limited lifetime warranty is called yeah
and what year was it oh my gosh I think
that was 1983 yourself and so so
southern
Anna's and so you've been stories kind
of happened to you and they've done
they've been similar as a whole time in
writing have poems in similar ways had
like kind of come upon you or is it a
little bit more I don't know is it a
different process than that holes are
more like a daily practice with me I
like I like poems they don't form either
more about sound and imagery voice who's
talking in my poems there's there often
some part of me that I didn't really
know was there you know some aspect of
personality that I'm kind of exploring
yeah who uses language a different way
maybe than my ordinary daily life self
so I like I like that kind of quick pop
of a poem and you start mostly with the
line or name
I like a line with an image in it okay I
like one time I was writing an article
about Charles writes poetry I really
like Charles Wright and I said something
in there and yes with you about the hand
of the image in the glove of sound and I
took that out over the review because I
thought it sound a little precious or
something but it reduces yeah
but for me I like that kind of fear sort
of in sort of indivisible great right
they come together but I'm I'm I
remember talking to Charles one time and
I asked him a lot of the same questions
you're asking me about composition I was
just like taken aback to the airport
after a reading I like plug in him for
everything you can tell me about how he
works and he says well you know after I
do it to your fourth draft and I I turn
it over to my ear yeah he said I drive
around town doing errands going to
stores stuff like that and I memorized
the poem and working on and then I just
start moving the words in the lines
around and then I start moving the lines
and the stances around just kind of
trying out I'm listening to the sonic
value I'm doing that so I guess that's a
good space to move on to review I mean
so when you're revising a poem are you
revising mostly by sound or I mean it's
like the sonic values is that where are
there different stages well you know
every poem has just presents different
troubles to me I guess these are some of
the questions I have to ask myself if
this is just for me I don't know that
these would be other people's problems
by any means but I'm asking myself who
the heck is talking
who is it because sometimes I just and I
mean that in a physical literal way I
have to see I have to see a figure
almost you know maybe it's me but it's
me when I'm 12
it's me with big red hair it's another
so I'm asking who is this person where
is she
are he sometimes I think I'm in a kind
of gender shift I like that because I
was a real tomboy as a little kid and I
think I kind of squashed that little
tomboy down and he likes to come back
and say things once in a while and he's
a little bit of a sassy smadi kid and I
like him so who is she where are we in
the poem I need to get located in
time-space
and what the heck is going on like what
dramatically is happening in the poem
and a lot of times I'm you know I'll
have a fix on one or the other of these
questions but I'm really feeling unclear
about the other so I kind of know
questions to ask myself and that's what
I do in there really early stages of
drafting the poem and trying to figure
out the answers to some of those and how
do these questions then translate into
like into the basic physical
manifestation of your writing are you
are you still in your notebooks working
yeah okay yeah fill in notebooks and are
you writing these questions in no now
I'm just what I'm doing is I'm just
getting my imagination a chore a task
instead I'm staring into space and
trying to see like where's the set where
is this unfolding trying to give myself
I'm so I'm interested in all this
material and I remember let's say you're
a poet but I mean it's also like you
knows it so you haven't so much up here
just that it doesn't happen on on the
page
doesn't happen it happens a lot yeah
going to the store and thinking about
for listening to me of your own sound
this is another hard things dr. Porter
yeah and see none of this takes place
with fictional fiction you're sort of
that you've got all that as you walk
into the first thing great great well
then so so what is your mode when you're
advising a story like how do you how do
you work through the drafts of the story
well with a story I'm really thinking a
lot more about why does this happen or
why did this happen in the past tense
actually have a lot of questions
thoughts
motivations of the characters or what
their relationships are like how did
they get to this I'm often trying to
think about a little some details of
backstory you know again you know all
these things it's really helped to have
heard myself ask my students these
questions for the last 30 years yeah
they're kind of in there this is yeah
the questions to ask yourself and but I
think what I'm mainly doing once I have
addressed some of these questions I mean
we have to do with inferiority and
psychology of people is in revision I'm
just trying to get the story to move
along I'm really paying most attention
to the pace and I think in that regard
now poetry and fiction maybe have a
little more similarities when you get to
that stage of revision where you're
starting to really start to tighten yeah
are we there now what that was talking
about no yes okay your bands so then
with the poem I flash mercilessly I'm a
slasher yes and I move things around but
often when I'm moving around is you know
I've got too many lines on
the landscape all in a row here I've got
ten lines about a freaking place where
we are the best boring but I sometimes I
won't cut them I'll just take four of
them and put them in a different place
and I don't worry too much about like
how to get back there because that's
easy to do later and same in fiction
what I'm really thinking about pacing
I'm thinking about you know like the
opening of the story I'll just start
with the scene that we're going to catch
back up to in the middle but because
it's got some interest I think
interesting dialogue or something
interesting is going on with the
characters I'm going to start there and
then circle back and then catch back up
to it midway through the story oh and
you're for that same cut that's typical
for me to UM move around like that so
I'm just going okay we've got a scene a
dialogue now we're going to have you
know how to dissolve start now we're
going to have scene where we've got some
dream or some thinking that we're going
to go back to dialog so I'm just kind of
having some syncopation of pacing things
and that kind of happens throughout your
books to write not if not only within
the story hood within a collection of
stories there's sort of that same
disadvantages of such as it seems or not
not repetition but like a kind of
allusion to the same places and time and
space
so I guess is that when you are when
you're revising the entire book is that
when you're putting together the book
itself is that also happening yeah okay
okay so have these two modes of revision
that sort of focus on pacing and moving
around any changes how they changed over
the course of your career I mean did you
like when you were first starting out
writing did you have to come to this
kind of way of revising or it did just
what was it there from the beginning no
it's been a slow gradual process in the
beginning was was there a different kind
of way
more you know we're doing it more
by-the-book kind of speaker was it oh
gosh I don't I don't know how I was
doing anything at the beginning I know
you know what my first book of poems I
had help
I've never had an editor again yeah like
I had with that very first book Larry
Lieberman at University of Illinois
press
he weeded out some of the weaker poems
but also helped me to shape up some new
things I was working on and put them in
help me with the arrangement and you
know I've never had help like that again
but that was very instructive yeah Kimmy
yeah he would write me these interesting
little letters were you explained you
know why he thought this article here
and this go there and this stanza needed
to be gone this was stupid it was just
so helpful to have somebody be such a
close reader with the scene I said if
you ever had them again ever so so do
people play a role in your revision
process now or is it pretty much just
you um well my husband reads everything
and he's really really tough critic
really really tough it's very good but
he I think he's smart reader and he also
kind of knows what I'm capable of and if
I don't measure up he'll tell me yes
yeah so you don't all right you're not
corresponding with other writers I have
I have a couple of good fiction writer
friends that I have shared work with and
another a novel I had a two book
contract this is the book of stories
before this one and they wanted the
second thing to be a novel the publisher
I told you who decided they were going
to quit this is fiction and they wanted
the second book to be a novel so I I
tried three times to write a novel and I
got two hundred pages in three times
yeah and I showed a couple of those
books to friends who are fiction writers
and they they confirmed for me that what
I thought was true the way I could
phrase it to myself is they didn't have
a big enough engine I like a short story
I'm I like to go cut I like short
stories - I was struck though in quake
right but like I was I was reading that
and I thought it was I mean it read to
me and helps me a lot like the way that
Jennifer Egan is explaining we do love
working out in like separate stories but
all kind of like it's an investigating
certain kind of dilemmas and an
interesting kind of metaphorical
noticeable is well thank you I was that
good positive yes yeah with that but I
was like I mean like what did she call
this or not I mean I just was wondering
you know it's not anyway it's just such
a there's very arbitrary but I think I
can compose them very much separately
I mean that they are related right and
amazing yeah they're weak stories yeah
they've all been linked yes I really I
love all the different possibilities of
ways to link stories but in terms of the
engine yeah I like a little small engine
that I feel like I can I can fix what's
wrong with a little small engine and I
don't know if I could the novel thing
it's kind of overwhelming for me to
think about yeah how much you have to
sustain how much should have how much
needs to drive a big novel and I love
novels I was really none but I'm
intimidated by the arc how huge it needs
to be and how much maybe you need to
know before you sit down right there
writing a tale any sort of research or
circle or otherwise
yeah like quake was a good example I
love doing all that research on the
gypsy culture in the country I just
loved it oh yeah
and that just really fed my story so I
was looking on it and there's new books
that has a dinosaur dig in it that was
really fun meet my husband I went on the
dig in Montana as part of the research
for that fun made especially they just
have that like dinosaur versus dinosaur
discovery or something this summer could
you see this formed with like some
private invest in private digger found
these like perfectly preserved fossils
of like a Tyrannosaurus Rex worth like a
Stegosaurus like right next to
tremendous oh that that you made fight
and so they stole it and like I said wow
there's only big folded adoption for
some ridiculous price really sort of the
debate about this just like a couple of
Famers or something a couple of like
hold the whole week creatures Wow didn't
sleep and insane fine in Montana you
know and that's right well what I
understood was that on this is
interesting but what I heard was um
all those glacial floods what happened
and they basically wash all these bones
over and fall there be like this giant
phone bed of you know 20 different
species but just because they've been
washed by the floods like that yeah up
the same place I just read those words I
guess then what a couple more questions
what revision but some and then so I
guess one of the like I've been reading
this book called the work of revision
which is a really interesting book kind
of tracing the history of revision so
much romantics up through the modernist
period and then kind of how textual
critisism works with it but and she was
sort of earnings Hannah Sullivan wrote
and she was sort of delineating kind of
three modes of vision one being a
creative like
joyce adding all the stuff Pacifica and
the other parts of the other season it's
the sort of excitable subtractive way
that you seem to do and then there's
that sort of substitution and I'm
wondering if their primary mode between
those three that you use for your
revision or is
combination hmm I would say I I really
kind of start with the excretion first
yeah and then go into the subtraction
and then probably this substitution it's
like the pink ring I do at the very end
okay and physically where where do these
processes happen I mean like you're
taking this way by having in the
notebook what does that happen on the
computer or that happen in those spaces
usually I've excised much of what I was
going to take out before I type it up so
I probably as I said I'll probably do
two or three handwritten drafts and I'll
rip actually rip the notebook page out
or and I have snow books and notebooks
where I I have a big X through the page
to so that I do not get confused that
I'm actually done with this version now
there's a if I look hard enough in the
notebook there is a later version of the
pause but I so I throw the old ripped
out pages in the back of the notebook
and there's a newer version somewhere in
there but the older ones are fatter and
often I'm awful you know experimenting
with line breaks than to you know what's
the shape shaping issues and and so just
to confirm that you're doing that in the
notebook and then I'll book still so and
then I feel like when I move it to the
computer I'm sort of getting to a place
where I want to look at it there's
something I'm sure you're going to hear
this with lots of writers my age that
there's something about when you type it
up that starts to make it look and
permanent especially for me in terms of
the shape of the poem the the line
length especially in a poem I am less
inclined to fiddle with line lengths
once I've got it on the
on the computer I do that is but for
some reason it still feels easier for me
to do it on the page could like to stick
my slashes in there okay and so once
they're actually broken into lines on
the computer yeah you don't have you
don't feel like you still have that
freedom - well I do I do I do experiment
or you know something I'll go oh this is
15 lines it's so close to us on it I
don't I help it along you know so then
there should be like another times or 15
money yeah okay so and then at that
point are the ponies ordered into the
way you would like them in the hotel not
never so how does that with that
processor
oh that's just another process of just
printing out all the poems and then just
living with them and that takes I know
maybe a year to maybe even longer
sometimes of experimenting with sections
you know the arrangement I'm working
right now in a book of prose poems and
I'm just really struggling with what's
what's even going to be in this book 14
so there's there's a number so once you
get as a computer are you putting like
all the poems from windows look in one
word file say or are you putting them
individually um no I don't put I each
poem is its own file until I really
start to make the book as a book okay
until you're like so it's just
technically then you play call that file
whatever the title of the poem is yeah
and then save it saved in a folder with
my folder is called home al and there
are some subfolders in their labors
um
for a book would you make us a folder
then or well then each book gets its own
file then okay yeah okay but it's so the
poems are kind of in one day folder and
then as they calculate into a book that
will be 1/5 exactly and if it when they
get published and I put them in another
file called published poems okay so I
don't get don't get confused and not
spending yeah so yeah and then there's
some old you know I have filed called
files called pawns Oh ate better just
like I'm never going to probably do
anything with them now but they're still
sitting there and is that the same that
same sort of transfer happened with
fiction - um yeah I mean I've got a file
in there just called stories in process
and I don't know if they're going to be
a book yeah and so we'll get back to
computer stuff a little bit more let me
just sort of talk a little bit move from
revision and talk a little bit more
about kind of organizational and if
we're already kind of talking about it
these things also mention any but so I
mean well okay but with the computer
then you know you move from your
notebook and then you type it up and is
that that sort of a moment of revision
for you - and then you have several
other different moments of revision when
it's on the computer but some of those
happen in paper because you print them
out right and then that's that
arrangement happens physically usually
first and oh look I will look at it I'll
come back to it over a period of a I
don't know a couple of weeks on the
computer then once it's in a computer
file and look at it probably tinker with
it a little bit more before and then
I'll start sending it out probably
scooter so fairly soon after I type it
up maybe a month too
yeah I there comes a point where I feel
like I'm making it worse yeah yeah my
tinkering is starting to make it worse
that's the only thing that stops me and
then I start sending it out and it's our
book right now no just individual poems
and then if it comes back rejected often
I'll tinker a little bit more and send
it back out again so you use the sort of
publication and submission process as a
sort of revision proper I do okay hmm
and then so okay then they come together
in one file as your focal saying in
between and that out and then the
publishers and it's a similar sort of
thing accusative subjective you can
revise again or that sort of once it's
in that file once you've got it there
you just sort of want to get to give it
a see um I hope probably revise it a
little bit more if it comes back
rejected but usually once it skips in
book form
um yeah it seems sort of settled to me
and often that this may be a awful the
case um the reason for that being that
I've probably moved on to another book
about it and that's another don't work
yeah yeah no an actual and I'm actually
compiling another book at that point
when I start to me one out and how many
books do you usually have going how many
projects at one time you usually have
two well I almost always have a book of
poems yes in process that I'm working on
like I said right now we'll keep trying
to shape up this book of prose poems and
then I almost always have a book of
fiction that's in process right now I'm
working on a ebooks novel novella thing
and and then you know I'm doing the
photos and also in terms of like
publishing individual pieces
I'm really doing those a lot okay
and then so in terms of just sort of
saving and archiving in your work
you think we talked a little bit about
this to keep your notebooks basically in
boxes on the shelf and then your files
are in a folder and they just stay in
the same folder and you put them to an
external drive yep importantly is there
any other kind of archival or backup
procedures that you go through for your
work or is that pretty much yes I guess
that's pretty much it I mean my
publishers I think have copies you know
they have PDF yeah of everything right
so I rely on them but those are not
going to go away I don't they send me to
prove now yes yeah okay and they used to
send you galleys or or pretty though
yeah huh
and where do you do much revision in the
best days not that one they don't like
it okay yeah yeah okay so then I guess
one question more and then I want to
talk kind of about computers
specifically but do you see kind of a
Miss talking listed is there was there
sort of thing you kind of delineate
stages in your own writing over the
course of your you know your stupid
writing so professionally do you see
distinct stages or do you think it's
just been kind of gradual you mean
that's where things have just changed
dramatically or like you know they could
have changed over like a couple of years
but I mean I could you can't would you
say there are stages or would you just
see it kind of and if there were
anything that kind of prompted some
changes well for those I guess it's
where I'm kind of filling
well I think it's mostly been gradual
that I've I've grown more comfortable
doing some revision work on the computer
and especially with the fiction and
maybe because fiction is still feels
like a newer form to me one shift that
has felt a little bit more dramatic with
composing is that I have found myself
and I'm working on short stories
actually doing some new composing work
right here while I'm sitting there like
out I'll be working on a story you know
thinking I'm typing in from my notebook
and actually I remember working on this
one story and I had written them
something a note to myself in my
notebook that said flush out her dream
right here and I had forgotten to do
that so I remember sitting here doing it
while I was typing in the story on this
into my word file and I thought when I
wrote was okay
and it sort of freed me up then to do
that more frequently to let myself do
some of the initial composing although I
still kind of like have a little cue
that what it's going to be you know like
there's a little hole that I forgot to
do or and I have a note to myself in the
notebook okay so do that I guess how
does was the difference in feel between
I guess Barry doesn't care does writing
with two-handed writing versus one yeah
what one of the things that I like about
doing it on the computer is I can close
my eyes which isn't really odd but I
like it and so it seems to lend itself
to
whoo somewheres not to dialogues or
actions but to real kind of interior
moments where I'm in a character's mind
and I want to replicate our thinking
process like I said what's the first
time I ever tried it was where I kind of
tried to render a dream but the
character had had so I close my eyes you
know he's Corsican type of rifle right
but I can't write with my icicle okay
you really invertible yeah yeah yeah
okay so in terms of computers generally
when did you when did they enter into
your writing process well when I I
remember when I moved to Lake Forest
College I knew were going to ask me this
I was trying to think about this the
other day and we got these when I wish I
could k-pro favorite okay have you heard
of those no oh my god they were these
huge grey boxes and they were given to
us this must have been 1980 right around
there 1980 at Lake Forest College all
the faculty got these k-pro computer
things and really all they did was word
processing so but I liked him I remember
a lot of the faculty were complaining
but I believe you know because I was
moving from I like a Selectric
typewriter something and this machine
was so much easier to do corrections and
everything yeah and so I took to the
computer right away I really liked it
you making me yeah okay that's very
really well I can't remember the exact
here somewhere I mean you started
teaching in Lake Forest in 79 so it was
right around there when we first moved
there yeah and that's all they did they
didn't do there was no internet or right
yeah we were just just WordPerfect yeah
did this
well the advent of this computer and
then maybe like the kind of more
prevalence of computers kind of change
your writing practices pretty
drastically eventually or well and the
you know the academic world I don't know
if I hadn't been in the Academy if I
would be have the same relationship with
technology as I do because everywhere I
went to teach I was presented with a new
computer when I walked in the door and
and it's nice and because you know Apple
made its money by habituation habitual I
seen people with Lauren trying to say no
to their to their technology yes that's
how they became so great you know you
know get all these freshmen hooked on
apples when they're in college because
they're in the labs and then the next
thing you know you've got generations
out there and so anyway I am the total
Mac person I love them I think they seem
really intuitive to me to use them but
and but I've grown up with them great I
mean so and then I guess what about the
software that you used you started with
the sort of basic word processing did
you move to an Apple word processing
software or was it like WordPerfect or
you remember I mean I can't even me no
no gosh I'm not going to be able to
remember all the different program names
but yeah and now are using Microsoft
Word uh-huh okay but you're also using
pages yeah so so you're looking between
software there has that been a newer
thing since the iPad or yeah I may get a
new iPad pretty soon up and I don't I
don't know if I want to buy another
Microsoft Word you know yeah I'm getting
agencies next time yeah it moves can't
afford to find great great
but I learned um Photoshop okay
when I was magazine editor
I edited Willow Springs for about six
years
and so I've learned that what's in 1990
he took over the editorship of that
magazine when I came out to Eastern and
they they were doing the magazine with
there was null computer technology the
woman who had done it before me was like
she was into the light board thing which
I had learnt which I had learned in
college I in journalism class you know
with the sticky pili thing you really
like you I actually saw this in high
school in my journalism class - yes and
I could not believe that that they had
no computer program or anything so a guy
in the journalism department gave me a
copy page maker to put on the computer
and I instantly fell in love with it
yeah I just oh I loved us I love doing
the art for the magazine I did the
covers you know I mean I found the art
and made the covers myself because there
was nobody else to do it right and so I
learned pagemaker at the very beginning
when it was just out and then she
probably know that became social so I
just kind of stayed with it on all these
years and now easily sorted out this one
of years Wow and you know I buy every
other Photoshop fests that's been my mo
I don't try to keep up with every single
new one so I'm on five now but I will
probably get seven with I'm a little
worried that they're not going to do
that anymore they seem to be moving
sabbatical a subscription basis you
really yeah how do you mean well you
know we buy it a lot for the digital
secures and I'm starting to hear that
there's you know they're offering it now
season you know basically pay a monthly
fee and get photos
or get in design or get the design suite
but that so I'm not sure how often if
they're going to be selling those like
student teachers kind of additions
anymore
Oh or if they're going to be charging a
subscription fee which in my mind is
going to be windmill expensive
assistance as we have so many topics it
might be cheaper overall for an
individual but interesting yeah so I'm
not sure I'm not actually positive about
that but I sort of have heard on the
wind that might be no wow that was okay
it's a tax write-off oh yeah yeah yeah
so you were you were pretty familiar
with computers from from pretty much
your most invisible professional career
as they became more prevalent in the
society at large did that effect I mean
I guess it affected probably your
correspondence with your editors and
whatnot in your saclink like that did
that affect anything in the way that you
write to do start to feel different it
writing feel different um it felt more
constant
I guess I'm my students at Vermont
College they want to send me their work
everything online now and I feel like I
cannot I cannot get away from sitting
here you know 10 hours 12 hours a day
and that's that part I I don't like as
much I I still I like reading you
knowing that in a comfy chair and I feel
like we're moving away from that now
because that's becoming less and I'm you
know I'm writing ebooks myself now so
yeah so I'm a culprit to free but I can
leave my iPad in a comfy chair
yes
I still like reading in bed but once I
discovered that I can read my iPad in
bed I was happy I am sort of interested
- I guess did sort of typographical or
more graphical things I mean you see
working familiar with PageMaker did that
did any of that like ability of the
computer to adjust or I mean like I like
I think in quake with those the breaks
that were kind of like speaks a lot my
kind of jagged lines I don't know where
those came from Aceves computer thing or
you don't talk about section breaks like
the breaks within the stories that would
be like yeah like section breaks they
had like kind of I think that might've
been the science book design or those
design okay but did any of that
influence your writing I mean did you
start to and then you obviously what
response and design aspects and layout
did that influence anything with your
poems I mean I know they also you know a
lot of them will have least the earlier
one some of them would move kind of tab
by tab and then I mean there's other
different sort of strategies in palms
too but there I don't know I mean I'm
trying to think about what you're asking
me because I just want remembering um or
if there's any particular way that that
changed in my writing itself yeah I mean
I don't think it wasn't I don't know
that I can say that it I guess when
you're writing in your note baby that's
the way to get when you're writing in
your notebook are you writing with sort
of indentation and other things like
that or are you pretty much down the
left margin to those who does that sort
of layout saying transfer to the
computer right you're right you know I
what little experimenting I've done
along those lines with poems I've done
on the computer screen sugar yeah I mean
that's I think my I know we're going to
talk about this later what I'm doing now
I'm doing these altered book pages right
you know if I showed you any of those
crystals are all blah
files but I'm doing these altered book
pages and those are that's where all
everything I know about Photoshop and my
poetry is like finally coming together
into something that feels more I don't
know my own yeah different so we can
talk about that everybody
so is that different than the photons
yeah okay yeah um what sort of for
tonight I'll show you
so I'm um I put these online I send this
is mainly what I've been publishing
lately I found this old encyclopedia up
here from the 30s and I've been scanning
the pages okay especially pages that
have a lot of graphic material in them
and yeah so I I put them on this website
but in a in a locked gallery cuz this is
how I share them then with editors oh ok
so let's see y'all try to find that it's
like Latino one here so Zenfolio is like
this like a webservice kind of yeah this
isn't really for photographers website
but I just liked it because it has a
really clean look yeah and their
slideshow mode is really nice yeah so
this is the book I'm doing with my
husband right now and these are his
these are his illustrations so I can
actually put this in slideshow you can
see that so this is my fiction project
okay that I'm busy the novella this is
yeah this I will only I haven't shared
this actually with any editors yet
because I'm only just putting this
online that's a section be lighter page
this is called a pull for stop so then
and then this story goes like this so
these are Rick's pieces and then I have
this little story that goes with these
characters in the book here and each
page I think of it as a little like
flash fiction yeah yeah so I kind of
think of them as linked flash fiction
and they're relating in some way to the
image oh yeah okay so that's that book
that book and I was telling you multi
encyclopedia and that's book of no ledge
and so this is how I send them out now
to editors hmm I'll probably send like
two or three of these pieces in you know
the online submission or whatever and
then I send them a link to this to this
gallery and the password that they need
to access it because the locked gallery
that way I can kind of track on you know
how many people are looking editors are
looking at myself at the same time right
and then when somebody takes a piece I
put these little asterisks this just
like screwed up things so they kind of
can realize all those are out of
commission then so that's what so now
I'm kind of actually putting a poem and
I hate all this fail stuff in here but
there's since then I'm actually kind of
replacing the text that was here in the
encyclopedia with a poem and and so
you'll do that in Photoshop like you'll
erase the text and then you'll are you
trying to match the font in some way it
looks like or at least kind of it I am
and then those are images from the text
originally yes actually they're from
like three different pages in the text
and then I've colorized them to Carlini
project it's really been fun I like I
like doing that you can see I've kind of
done a little bit of a racer stuff in
here yeah and then this part is my poem
over here so I like as I said put these
in slideshow cos they're come out water
but I kind of like having a mix of what
would be encyclopedia language with naps
talk kind of I like going back and forth
so that's this has been where I've
really started to use the technology
much more than I was before so I have
all those people this is the straight
cyclopdia man stuff and I hope they
kind of talk back and forth to each
other the language yeah no I see what
you're saying my language here in their
language and well I'm sorry it's sort of
like contextualizes and sort of
decontextualize isn't it yeah yes my
little conversation with proof I've been
reading proof to shared I see improves
there on a timeout right now anyway
that's Alaska thing looks like I like
the pate I like the pages from the
encyclopedia that have all this graphic
material so I can um I kind of take what
was you know I what I have I put all
these kind of romance words around in
this one timber Wolf's love nipped not
skok soulmate I gave them kind of
anything yeah different a merciless
but a person would have to sort of go in
there and look a little bit right that's
ready to see yeah I mean yeah I mean it
is to pay attention salt that's that's
where things have sort of evolved
computerized from
and how does that I mean what's the like
does it feel different is it disorder
that seem like the same creative process
for you I mean I mean it's visual and
textual so there's that but in terms of
using the computer to make is that a
change well so the way I've been I have
some really interesting different ways
that I've been doing these that have
never been even remotely like working on
the palms of stories so I'll print out
first the original scans and black and
white and that's what I carry around in
my little notebook you know I'm so
fixated to the notebook there so I'm
carrying those around the notebook and
then I just actually just start
scribbling on the pages scribbling stuff
out I'm one of the things that I'm kind
of doing with this book project with the
encyclopedia is this is my version of a
Collected Poems of Nance Van Winkle so
I'm kind of mining some of my early
poems because I the idea of doing a
collected or selected or something is
kind of boring to me actually okay but
this made it more interesting to do yes
because I'll just pull out oh I always
like this Danson yeah I like to stand
and then I you forget the rest of that
foam you know but these five lines I
like so I'll sprinkle them in there and
it's been fun to kind of find the visual
material that I think they fit with yeah
so anyway I'm so wealth of human
knowledge from thirty thirty well
exactly exactly and you know I feel like
I'm kind of talking I am I said one of
the things that's going on in this
project is I'm talking back to history
in a way and say no that's not right and
I like that I like that Marisa and I
guess in some ways the software allows
you more
purchase on making them deletion and
adjustment exactly and it would have
really crossing out or like board right
yeah
and the erase you're saying you know
that a lot of people are doing yeah that
seems like you know I'm good friends
with Mary rueful through an amazing
resource every yeah I feel like I could
run up Mary rueful I'm not doing that
I'm not going there there are people who
are doing that so much better
I've always been a fan of it that Robbie
off to paradise block leashes around uh
uh how did this team like you're gonna
yeah and I weigh who did one like oh he
didn't really happy birth mirrors yeah a
lot I think maybe too many people jumped
on the eraser its
bandwagon it's but it's hot I mean it's
really I mean to do it in the latest
miracle so it is really really hard I
mean like yeah here's something area was
all set the way I do it is I look at the
page and then pretty soon if I just
stare at it for a while a few words
slowed up good okay oh oh
eliwood so words flowed up into a lot of
these questions in the course of it
Oh can you find your files like if
you're looking for like a certain phone
on your computer would you if you have
difficulty locating them or are you is
your organization such that you pretty
much know where things are I have lost I
have lost things and yeah almost every
week I have a little battle because I
can't remember why I called something
yeah yeah do you worry at all about the
security or some fixity of these digital
files no no you mean somebody else
accessing them or something that Jeremy
or the kind of fidelity of them I guess
I mean visitors I mean you do say that
you have floppy disks and old Word
Perfect documents or something that you
can't access that is that a concern to
you or you just think that will kind of
take care of itself
um it's not a concern to me maybe it
should be no I don't I actually don't
think it should be but um and I'm I'm
wanting to know that so okay but I mean
that yeah there's definitely things we
can do but I mean it's one of those
things that I think well I guess the
other question is have the changes in
computers I mean like you know probably
in the 98 90s early 90s computers
crashed much more often more likely to
lose work too bad ever influence the way
that you work on computers or was that
were you pretty much kept the same
strategies I have pretty much kept the
same strategy she no I've never had a
really bad thing happen where I've lost
the hard drive or anything like that I
know I know and you know they got you
bigger they really do I I just I love
all their products as I could so a few
questions are correspondences teaching
all the way to sever sabbatical couple
episode m and another view
so you have you ever correspondent very
much in like like physical letters has
that ever been a person or but I mean
play to your writing I don't need to
know you know the personal
correspondence not so much but I mean
like writing wise to realize that ever
no physical letters I well like I was
telling you with that first book of
poems I've kept all the letters that he
wrote to me about revision yeah I don't
know they just they're very dear to me
that somebody took that kind of time
with me and and then I have a good
friend who's a poet I think I mentioned
her to you Jennifer Boyd muse and she
really loves the physical letter and
I've kept all her letters that she's
written me over the years because
they're just beautiful and and it just
always seems like just the idea that
somebody is writing this just to me you
know the three page letter with her
thoughts and ruminations about things
and they're just so beautifully written
but she would take the time to do that
you know it's it seems like a treasure
thing because it's passing but do I do
it
do you have any similar feelings for
anything yes you have email but you to
feel fear about oh I do keep some emails
I have you know files these emails that
I keep from certain people a minute and
it's a corollary to that do you feel
like a this is an odd question but do
you have any sort of feelings towards
your digital files about yet your poem
you feel like are they dear to you in
the same way maybe a notebook would be
here you or no no the notebook is dearer
okay I don't know I don't know what
that's weird touch it is could it be
part of it is
yeah there's me I don't know yeah it's
one of those one of those things I don't
know if that will change
like if someone never had but this is
cool in the future it would have the
special folder on the desktop that just
to talk to me but you know I try to be
careful that I've always got a hardcopy
somewhere the material I'm working I
like this book that I'm doing with my
husband okay
and there they all are because and the
way that well to finish that that
thought about just being careful because
it's just if things go awry here I
really I don't want to lose the work
completely free so I try to make sure
that I have a hard copy it's not always
the most recent copy yeah but there's
there's the coffee right so and with
this book I did all of the arranging of
it I stuck them on that wall in the
hallway okay and all the pages were on
that wall and I was moving I had little
sticky things on the back and I was
moving them around to make the sections
of the book for it was up there for like
three months
yeah three three months off so you would
just would you come home and see them
and make a few changes or was it
basically be a dedicated time that you
go to it er um well it was I was at that
stage with the book or I had all these
pages but I wasn't exactly sure you know
how I was going to arrange the the
chronology again on the story yeah so I
started experimenting with different
orders of things by putting this China
sections on the on the boards on the
wall that way yeah moving them around so
because s so before I had each page as
its own file in there and now and now
they have sections to
section I think they're five sections in
the book and those came from the wall
yeah okay so but I had to I could not
figure out a way to look at that many
pages on the screen at one time and I
mean actually see the print okay that
was yeah I felt like I the technology
wasn't allowing me to see the big
picture the way I needed to I'm sure
they're coming after they're here yeah
exactly yeah you too big wall this is
you and if Mac makes it I'm buying it is
only going to be a million dollars yeah
I guess we did talk a little bit about
your teaching and that you do correspond
by email with your students mostly is
that um now if they insist on it okay
I'm sending me their work as attachments
and everything I'll read it that way I
don't like doing it with the poet's with
the fiction people I was much much
rather they send me their work in the
mail okay and usually they're okay with
them you kind of take it and not have to
be connected and not have to and then
yeah yeah and I just I do not like
writing my comments laundress in with
the blackboard program or any of those
the college has that available to us and
I have done track changes in word I know
how to use that okay but I just I just
like to scribble in the largest right so
something that in that aspect of your
work and your life like you just
ultimately prefer physical
correspondence pull in yeah cool yeah
okay
yeah and then I guess the other thing
with with like writing and distraction I
guess is it's like when are you
connected to the internet when you're
writing do you ever have to like do it
like disconnect turn off your Wi-Fi or
something
Bravo one concern for you before you use
they are you think looking things up
while you're writing wrong that's a good
question um I don't like to be
disconnected from the net anymore yeah
it's terrible yeah I like to check in
with my peeps all the time now three and
yeah I I mean I use the dictionary on
here all the time because it's just so
much faster yeah elated so it's a tool
whether in whatever writing space you're
in is be it notebook or not you're still
using experience also assist you
yeah and I'm always I've always got
something going on that's like what you
know like right now and talking to
agents and if they email me if I see an
email come in while I'm actually working
on something I've got to go see with
that so that is that from my agent right
great um so present in that distraction
point of it's not a real concerns of you
and you see you are producing closes it
once more when I was younger but I guess
maybe I'm learning how to how'd it go
back and how to disconnect from it and
go back to my work pretty fast then has
there been something found to help do
that mean like what we need if you're
distinguishing between your younger
working and now I guess maybe just like
a lot of younger people I'm just more
used to being attached to it you know I
I'll have my I'll be doing something on
my iPad communicating with somebody or
talking on Facebook or whatever well
Rick and I are watching a movie at night
so I'm there's much more multitasking
sort of way to compartmentalize yeah
seems pretty seamless yeah when I guess
that's question about teaching like when
you when you've had now you're probably
getting students to groan
only with the computer right and that
changed your relationship to it I mean
has that sort of changed your idea about
what it does its effects anything like
that
well it's changed to the sense that and
when students talk to me about their own
composing process and of course they
they do everything on the computer they
don't they don't ever a lot of them
write anything at all in longhand yes I
don't even know if they can and and so I
I'm ok with that I feel like I've sort
of made my peace that they if people are
perfectly able to write to find a good
composition process that works for them
that doesn't have to do with paper and
pens at all and thought I'm accepting of
that you know I don't try to like shove
my process off or say to Phyllis have
you ever thought you might like to write
it on a piece of paper first let's know
why I know I know that I'm I'm hanging
onto something that's if you were to pen
the pan of the paper to me they have
some there's something else going on
between the eye and the hand and the
page you know yeah and I still feel that
when I'm working
especially on poems that there's
something happening between the eye and
the fingers and and the page that's very
tactile that eyes I'm hanging on to that
I like and so you so you would say read
it for those that are only composing on
the computer and not never going to
handwriting or never using handwriting
at all that's what they're missing that
sort of Andy I don't know I don't think
they necessarily are missing it I think
they've they probably learn or are
learning to a step in the composing
process you know that maybe that thing
where you're writing with your eyes
closed yeah I mean the sake but if they
grow up with that and so they get the
same whatever imaginative connection
with the keyboard do you find that there
as open to revision as maybe an older
student well they can be made to they
can make something and that's just part
of the learning process right you don't
think if anything distinct to this
generation no I think they just have too
many of them some of them get it right
away that that revising can actually
make a work better yeah you know I've
been working with this woman right now
who came in saying that she doesn't like
to revise because she likes to just sit
down write everything out really fast in
one big draft and her stuff is a mess
and so it's my personal mission with her
to help her to come to believe that
actually revising or working in some
other manner you know like maybe having
writing off scene at a time what would
benefit the work but she's very young
and her first she never she didn't even
have an undergraduate degree in the
writing fall
she's starting it yeah Claire one yeah
okay well so that's kind of discussion
to have her about the programs and but I
guess you have you have a number of
distinct indeed being a sort of primary
of computer assisted project but you
have several going at the same time
seems including the collected your
novella are there other projects as well
okay and are they are they supplanting
your fiction and poetry writing or are
they sort of just in addition to I am
wrestling with this question myself I
think poetry right now the new poetry is
kind of going into the
so these altered book pages done doing I
have four four of those projects going
on right now and I am working on a book
of regular poems of prose poems but the
all the fiction I'm working are all
ebooks now I just completed novella not
this one but a different one that's an
e-book that's in the form of a scrapbook
photograph album and that's that's the
one I'm kind of taught the agents about
okay and they're going to and you you
you have only you don't expect to see a
physical form at all either this is the
question that we are trying to work
through I don't care about seeing it as
a print book but apparently the
publishers don't want to take a book
unless they can also have it as a print
book because they don't make any money
on the ebooks so yeah so an agent
doesn't want to take me on at the client
unless I am doing the print book and the
e-book is a sort of bonus okay
so that's what we're kind of going
around and around about and then I think
well maybe I'll just go out there and do
it
Oh try to do it with an e-book publisher
who is just doing that so I'm just
trying I just I'm just this is all new
to me and I new territory and I'm just
trying to navigate it myself right now
I don't know what I'm doing yeah what is
in in terms of like the process and the
competition everything it still seems
pretty much you know computer mouse
computer that is so like account well I
mean the computer is a big part of this
but still writing the notebook enforcing
or is it a lot of that still happening
are the ebooks happening on the computer
no I'm storing the text part in the
notebook how does the sort of visual
aspect relate fact here writing
especially sort of maybe I mean you use
a lot of imagery in your poems in a
musician but now you're actually using
images so what's what's that what's that
feel like are you so using them in the
same way to use imagery or is it a
totally different well I mean you hit it
right on the head that's it exactly I
mean everything I loved about poetry
that you know the image things yes now
I'm making actual images and you know
I'm putting a little bit of text in
there and you know now I'm starting your
ruffle with well that's too much text
you know it's everything that's
happening now has gotten to be less less
and less tests yes trying I'm trying to
find the right balance between the
visual component on this on the piece
and certain that sort of means minimal
text I think yeah so that they don't
fight each other I mean so what is that
I mean what is like how do you find the
right language for that what sort is
that I mean that seems like a different
but different almost a different things
in writing poetry and yeah yeah and that
I mean see see see just this is what for
me when I turned 60 and I I'm doing this
work it's made it exciting again like
when I was 20 yeah because I am language
of Scott ins it's been refreshed by this
new sort of interjection of the actual
visual material in the same location
with the text and it's made it like a
brand new thing for me and just I don't
know I feel like oh good now I can get
through to my 80s okay and
being barred you didn't okay so what
kind of too far questions if you didn't
have that facility with the computer
that you have and that you developed
from working with pagemaker and or if
you just have not worked with in the
computer do you think you would have
turned to visual art in a physical
format but it's okay no it would have
been too much to learn I think I mean it
still feels like a lot to learn I mean I
take classes every week I'm taking
online classes I mean I still can't get
how to do text on a path what's wrong
with me I can't make my paths good okay
yeah I'm not but anyway so I take these
little online classes to photoshop can
take any you I mean your husband's an
artist you have any sort of art
instruction as well yeah oh yeah okay
yeah for me and from him yeah and I've
been taking this like regular college
classes two-for-one I've caught a buck
now for a semester when they asked me to
come out there I said well yes I'll come
but Stevens will be alright if I sat in
on an art class while I'm there I wanted
to take some kind of photography class
oh but they weren't offering anything so
I took a film editing class instead but
anyway I just I felt like I just needed
to be in that environment with visual
artists where they're talking about
competitions yeah because that's I'm
starting at the tap beginning place yeah
this composition and design great great
no I think my husband comes in I invite
him to come home early a couple nights a
month and I fly in with some wine and he
steps here and I show them the pieces
that I'm working on the some of these
photos or whatever and I'll fit and I'll
say it can I just just if you don't like
a piece just tell me and we'll move on
so this is what I'll do a go next but
then when he likes a piece will explain
to me what he thinks is working and it's
all about composition and design
and that plane is America for you that's
what I need to learn - I think that's
good oh okay got quite a bit thank you
oh thank you your questions really good
thanks for listening to me blablabla no
no no I think it's good it's going to be
hard now you're going to have to edit
all this huh okay